Today's דף daf is צדי זין Tzadi Zayin and we pick up
at the very bottom of צדי ו עמוד ב Tzadi Vav Amud
Bet
and we had been talking about the issue in the משנה Mishna
that if you find new תפילין tefillin which then you cannot take
them home on שבת Shabbat because maybe they're not תפילין tefillin maybe
they're really some type of an amulet
and new presumably means that they don't have the knots made on
them as we'll see in a minute or that it's clear that
knots were never made were never made on them to begin with
meaning you know
anyway but that's that's new. The גמרא Gemara says why is that
like we have a whole discussion about finding blue strings of תכלת
techeilet in the marketplace that you can assume that if they were
made the whole right way and cut at the right length and
everything you could assume that they were done correctly so why shouldn't
we say the same thing here? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
אמר רבא Ella Amar Rava
two lines from the bottom of צדי ו עמוד ב Tzadi Vav
Amud Bet so rather רבא Rava says טורח ולא טורח טרחי. Torach
v'lo torach tarchi.
The question of do we say nobody would go to such an
effort unless it was the real thing? That's a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. So טורח torach means you know they would or they wouldn't
go to such an effort if it were the real thing if
it weren't the real thing. דתניא De-tanya taught in the ברייתא Baraisa
המוציא תפילין מכניסן זוג זוג HaMotzei tefillin machnisam zug zug אחד איש
ואחד אשה echad ish v'echad isha if you find תפילין tefillin you
can bring them in one pair at a time whether man or
woman. Top of צדי זין עמוד א Tzadi Zayin Amud Alef אחד
חדשות ואחד ישנות echad chadashot v'echad yeshanot so we taught this yesterday
the woman part but now we're focusing on the issue of the
new ones whether new or old דברי רבי מאיר divrei Rabbi Meir
that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says ורבי יהודה אומר אוסר בחדשות
ומתיר בישנות. v'Rabbi Yehuda omer oser b'chadashot u'matir b'yeshanot. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says
new are no good but old ones are good and that's the
position of our משנה. Mishna. So you see there's a debate between
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir whether in something
that's made to look just like תפילין tefillin you know maybe it's
not a hundred percent proof it doesn't have the straps and the
knots but anyway otherwise it's a black square leather box you know
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says obviously nobody would go to that
effort and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is still concerned that it might
be an amulet. So they are exactly debating that point. אלמא Alma
you see from that מר סבר טורח אינש mar savar torach inish
one says a person would go to effort even if it weren't
the real thing ומר סבר לא טורח אינש u'mar savar lo torach
inish and the other says people would not go to such an
effort if it were not the real thing. And therefore the position
that those strands of ציצית tzitzit those strands of string that are
blue and תכלת techeilet you could assume that they were done properly
as ציצית tzitzit and dyed properly as ציצית tzitzit that is the
position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that we assume that
nobody would go to such an effort unless it was actually real.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this והשתא דתני אבוה דשמואל בר רב יצחק v'hashta de-tanei avuha d'Shmuel
bar Rav Yitzchak but now the story's going to change because the
father of שמואל בר רב יצחק Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak teaches the
following ברייתא. Baraisa. Wait who's the
father of שמואל בר רב יצחק?
Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak? אבוה דשמואל בר רב יצחק? avuha d'Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak?
like יצחק Yitzchak
I thought it
was
because it's actually true I would have said
it's
I wasn't parsing it
I wasn't parsing it I thought it was I thought the בר
רב יצחק bar Rav Yitzchak was going on אבוה דשמואל avuha d'Shmuel
like שמואל's Shmuel father the son of רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchak. Oh
that makes sense.
That's how I read it. Right. No יצחק Yitzchak was was
יצחק Yitzchak then שמואל's Shmuel father then שמואל. Shmuel. That's how I
read it. What? Yeah that makes sense. Yeah that's what I understood.
Anyway אלו הן ישנות Elu hen yeshanot the following are considered old
כל שיש בהן רצועות ומקושרות kol she-yesh ba-hen retsuot u'mekusharot they have
straps and the straps are knotted. חדשות Chadashot the new ones right
with the יוד yud and the דלת dalet new יש בהן רצועות
ולא מקושרות yesh ba-hen retsuot v'lo mekusharot they might have straps and
they're not knotted. Okay so I had already alluded to that ahead
of time because that's based on the end of the גמרא Gemara
but now the גמרא Gemara says that changes things. Why does that
change things? דכולי עלמא לא טורח אינש de-kulei alma lo torach inish
everybody agrees that in principle we would say that you you know
you wouldn't go to the effort to make these boxes if they
weren't real תפילין tefillin so that the problem of new ones meaning
the גמרא Gemara is not fully spelled out but what it's saying
is the problem of new ones is not what we've been saying
all along. The problem of new ones is not that they might
be amulets. Everybody agrees nobody would make these things that look like
these boxes of תפילין tefillin if it wasn't real תפילין. tefillin. The
problem is how can you wear the תפילין tefillin home on שבת
Shabbat if it doesn't have a knot? Okay so how you going
to wear it? Meaning the knot does not just mean it doesn't
have the יוד yud or the דלת dalet it presumably also means
it doesn't have the whole you know way it's made well if
it doesn't have the דלת dalet on the head it doesn't stay
on the head and if the יד yad doesn't have the loop
there's nothing to tighten it. So the problem of new ones is
not concerned that it might be an amulet the problem is that
there's no way to wear it without a שבת Shabbat violation because
you can't make knots on שבת. Shabbat. So then the obvious question
is going to be so then why does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
say it's okay if that's the problem? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. וליענבי מיענב v'leanvei mi'enav so the גמרא Gemara says
so go ahead actually I'm sorry I sort of asked this question
which then alludes to the next question and the answer of the
next question. So okay, there's no knot, but why not make like
a bow? There's a way to wear something like you put on
your shoes, you don't make a knot. So put on your תפילין
tefillin by making a bow and not making a knot. So אמר
רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda זאת אומרת עניבה פסולה בתפילין. zos omeres
aniva psula b'tefillin.
That shows you that you cannot make a bow for the תפילין
tefillin and therefore to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah. And again,
presumably what allows you to wear it on שבת, Shabbos, even if
שבת Shabbos is לאו זמן תפילין, lav zman tefillin, is that this
is considered a normal way דרך מלבוש derech malbush it becomes like
a piece of clothing. But as we learned before, you can't wear
it on a part of the body you normally can't wear it,
that's not considered the normal way this is worn. So similarly you
can't wear it with a bow if it's normally worn with a
knot, and that would not be considered דרך מלבוש. derech malbush. So
since it's not you can't be יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah with
a bow, it's also not an acceptable way, a legitimate way to
wear it on שבת. Shabbos. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, did
I skip a line? No. רב יהודה לטעמיה דאמר עניבה קשירה מעליא
היא. Rav Yehuda l'taamei d'amar aniva kshira maalya hi. רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda actually goes according to his reasoning, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that
says that the new ones are no good. So in order to
answer the question of why not make a like a bow, it's
because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda holds that a bow in הלכות שבת
hilchos Shabbos counts as a knot. So therefore it's not a solution.
The problem is you can't wear it because you can't, you know,
bind it on your arm. And it's שבת Shabbos and you can't
make a knot. So why not make a bow? So the answer
is for רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who that's exactly
a bow is a problem in שבת Shabbos as we'll see in
a minute. And therefore that's not a solution for him and that
exactly explains the debate of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and רבי מאיר.
Reb Meir. Presumably רבי מאיר Reb Meir is saying you could wear
it because a bow is okay on שבת, Shabbos, and רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda is saying you can't wear it because a bow is
not okay on שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara now says like
this. טעמא דעניבה קשירה מעליא היא. Taama d'aniva kshira maalya hi. So
you're telling me that the reason רב יהודה Rav Yehuda doesn't let
you wear these new ones home is because you'd have to make
a knot or bow and even a bow is considered a knot
and it's a שבת Shabbos problem. הא לאו הכי עניב להו? Ha
lav hachi aniv lehu? But if that were not true, then if
he didn't have the שבת Shabbos issue, he actually using a bow
would have been a solution of how you could have worn this.
So now we're going to get to this question: can a bow
be legitimate for תפילין? tefillin? Like we were sort of circling back
to what we said a minute ago. ואמר רב יהודה בריה דרב
שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב: V'amar Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar
Shilas mishmei d'Rav: didn't רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the son
of again רב שמואל בר שילת Rav Shmuel bar Shilas says another
the son of no over there it makes sense, not the father
of, the son of רב שמואל בר שילת Rav Shmuel bar Shilas
in the name of רב, Rav, קשר של תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני
הוא? kesher shel tefillin halacha l'Moshe miSinai hu? That the knot of
תפילין tefillin is a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe miSinai. ואמר רב
נחמן ונוייהם לבר: V'amar Rav Nachman v'noyehem l'var: their beauty is on
the outside, which basically means that
when you make the knot at the back of the head that
looks like a דלת, dalet, or when you make the knot on
the של יד shel yad that looks like a יוד, yud, it
has to be a visible דלת dalet and a visible יוד yud
and it has to be, you know, exposed so that somebody could
look at it and see it. So how is that relevant? So
the גמרא Gemara understands like this: there are two questions. One is
what defines a knot? Is a can a bow equal a knot?
But the other is what does it have to look like? So
the גמרא's Gemara question is: I don't get it. You're telling me
that
so the question is you find this on the street, can you
wear it home or not? So according to רבי מאיר Reb Meir
on שבת, Shabbos, רבי מאיר Reb Meir says you can wear it
home. Presumably he's going to allow you to do some type of
a bow because you can't do a real knot.
So how would a bow ever be acceptable for a knot of
תפילין? tefillin? And now it's asking the same question in רב יהודה.
Rav Yehuda. And you're telling me רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says you
can't do it because a bow counts as a knot for הלכות
שבת. hilchos Shabbos. But forget הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. How could you
do a bow that actually is a legitimate knot of תפילין? tefillin?
Even if a bow equals a knot, it doesn't look like the
דלת, dalet, it doesn't look like the יוד. yud. So that's, you
know, not the world's biggest question. The גמרא Gemara has an answer.
The גמרא Gemara says דעניב להו כעין קשירה דידהו. D'aniv lehu k'ein
kshira dideyhu. Fine, you make it look like the knot, you make
it look like a דלת, dalet, you make it look like a
יוד. yud. Now does that mean you're really יוצא yotzei or not
is not clear because again remember in order to legitimately be wearing
it home on שבת, Shabbos, it's not clear that you have to
a hundred percent say you're doing that this would otherwise constitute the
מצוה. mitzvah. It has to be enough within the bounds of normal
that it's considered a legitimate type of a clothing, like it's a
legitimate wearing. So well that women, that's the issue that גמרא Gemara
discussed as long as women were theoretically permitted even if they weren't
obligated, right? That was discussed yesterday.
Right, fine, but as long as it's not considered bizarre, it's not
like it's considered like, you know, wearing a tie on your leg,
that would be okay. So the question here when the גמרא Gemara
says is in theory and this is ultimately what the גמרא's Gemara
going to say according to רבי מאיר Reb Meir why you can
wear it is that in theory what you could do is to
get to deal with the שבת Shabbos issues is you make a
bow, assuming a bow is not a שבת Shabbos violation, that's for
רבי מאיר Reb Meir as opposed to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, for
the דלת dalet or the יוד. yud. And they weren't there, you
came late, yes that's correct, and and you make it look like
a דלת, dalet, make it look like a יוד. yud. Now that
doesn't mean you'd be יוצא yotzei that way necessarily the rest of
the week, the גמרא's Gemara ambiguous, maybe the גמרא Gemara is saying
that, but at least it means it looks normal enough. That to
wear it on שבת Shabbos is considered to be a normal wearing
of תפילין. tefillin. Okay, and that's the גמרא's Gemara answer which is
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says why you can do it, you
make the bow, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can't make a
bow for שבת Shabbos issues, but in theory there would be a
way in which you could do it that it would look acceptable
enough to wear it home on שבת. Shabbos. One minute, let me
just read a little bit more. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, no, so that's, so what did, now I just want to
say this issue that the קשר kesher is הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai, רש"י Rashi says what aspect of the קשר kesher is
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, רש"י Rashi says all of the
three letters: the ש' shin on the תפילין, tefillin, which isn't exactly
a קשר, kesher, the ד' daled and the י'. yud. תוספות Tosafos
says, if you look at the first line of תוספות, Tosafos, פירוש
הקונטרס, Peirush Hakuntres, הלכה למשה מסיני היכו עשויה שדומה לד' Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai heichu asuyah she'domeh l'daled ובטביעתו עושה כמו ש' u'v'tvi'ato oseh k'mo
shin פ' רצועה קבועה בהם בראשו כפוף ודומה לי' p'ritsuah k'vuah bahem
b'rosho kofuf v'domeh l'yud הרי שדי. harei shaddai. Okay, ואין נראה לי
דאין הלכה למשה מסיני אלא השי"ן בלבד. v'ein nireh li d'ein Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai ela ha'shin bilvad. So there's an interesting מחלוקת machlokes whether
all the emphasis that we do with the knotting of the ש'
shin and the of the ד' daled and the י' yud or
whatever, is that really הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai? Because that's
all on the רצועות, retzuos, and maybe the only הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai part is the actual ש'. shin. Okay, so that's,
but clearly the גמרא Gemara says whatever it is, we know the
knots have to look like a ד' daled and a י' yud
and they have to be visible that way and says fine, so
that's what you did, you made a bow that would look like
it and that's enough to make it acceptable to wear home on
שבת.
Shabbos. Yes. And there are other things we do, like for instance
we wrap it around seven times and then you put it around
your finger. But if you saw somebody that didn't wrap it around
seven times, wrapped it around once, you'd say you're not wearing תפילין.
tefillin.
So, you know, do you have to do all of it? I
don't know the answer. I don't know how much it has to
look exactly like you wear it during the week, you know, in
order for it to be considered a legitimate wearing on שבת. Shabbos.
Look, people that wear clothes in funny ways, there's a degree of
tolerance of difference, right? So the point is, at a certain point
though, it's not considered wearing it at all. So even if it's
not a hundred percent normal, there's a tolerance of a range, right?
So the, I don't know the exact limits of that range.
But clothing is, תפילין tefillin is more
of a ritual, you know, it's gotta be. I understand, but the
way we're saying it is, yes, it's a ritual, but ultimately it's
worn, so that allows us on שבת Shabbos to look at it
as clothing.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב חסדא
אמר רב, Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav, so now that we're talking
about תפילין, tefillin, we are going to, and we talked before about
ציצית tzitzis and finding ציצית tzitzis on the street, and can you
assume or blue strands and can you assume they're כשר kosher ציצית
tzitzis or not, we have a somewhat similar discussion by תפילין. tefillin.
Let's take a look. אמר רב חסדא אמר רב הלוקח תפילין ממי
שאינו מומחה, Amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Haloke'ach tefillin mi'mi she'eino mumcheh,
if you buy תפילין tefillin from somebody who is not an expert.
So meaning the scenario is, as is clear from the continuation of
the discussion, you're buying it from a, I don't know, a wholesaler,
okay, and you're going to retail. But this wholesaler didn't write it
himself, he goes around to twenty different סופרים sofrim and collects and
buys their תפילין, tefillin, and you buy it from the wholesaler. Now
this guy is not a מומחה. mumcheh. Now מומחה mumcheh does not
mean expert in this context; it means somebody who has like proven
credentials. Okay, you don't know, you can't be certain that this guy,
everything that he's selling is a hundred percent כשר, kosher, that he's
checked it himself and it's כשר, kosher, whatever, you don't know that.
You're going to have to do some of the checking yourself. So
what do you do? בודק שתים של יד ואחת של ראש. Bodek
shtayim shel yad v'achas shel rosh. So you check, you have to
check three: either two of the של יד shel yad and one
of the של ראש, shel rosh, or שתים של ראש ואחת של
יד, shtayim shel rosh v'achas shel yad, or two of the של
ראש shel rosh and one of the של יד. shel yad. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: מה נפשך? Ma nafshach? One minute. Make
up your mind. אי מחד גברא זבנינהו, Im michad gavra zavnin, if
this wholesaler actually bought from one supplier, so לבדוק או שלש של
יד או שלש של ראש, livdok o shalosh shel yad o shalosh
shel rosh, why do you need a two-one? You know, if it's
all one סופר's sofer תפילין, tefillin, check any three, even if they're
all three של ידs shel yad or three של ראשes. shel rosh
The idea of three being three is a חזקה. chazaka. So one
random check doesn't prove to you that all the stuff here is
reliable. Okay, but if it's from one supplier and you check three
randomly selected תפילין tefillin and they all look good, you can assume
they're all good. The normal idea that three is a חזקה. chazaka.
So why does it have to be two and one? You could
even be three of the same type if it's all from the
same סופר. sofer. If he could write a של יד shel yad
correctly, he could write a של ראש shel rosh correctly. ואי מתרי
תלתא
גברי זבנינהו, V'im mitrei tlata gavra zavnen, and if the point is
that he buys from multiple suppliers, two or three guys, so
כל חד וחד איבעי בדיקה, ko chad v'chad iba'ei bdika, every pair
you should have to check, every single pair!
Because you don't, I don't mean like the actual פרשה, parsha, no,
no, no.
So every single pair of תפילין tefillin would require its own checking
because each pair might have come from a different סופר. sofer. So
what's the idea of two of this and one of that? It
doesn't make any sense. So the גמרא Gemara says: לעולם מחד
גברא זבנינהו, Le'olam michad gavra zavnin, fine, he buys from one supplier.
ובעינן דמממחי, U'v'inan d'mitmachei, that word מומחה, mumcheh, he has to be
again not made expert, but he has to be sort of validated,
proven, בשל יד ובשל ראש. b'shel yad u'v'shel rosh. So basically it's
an interesting idea: you need three, like any idea that's a form
of חזקה, chazaka, you need to do three random samples, but you
have to make sure maybe this guy
doesn't understand something about the של ראש shel rosh or doesn't understand
something about the של יד. shel yad. He writes a beautiful כתב,
ksav, but, you know, maybe I don't know. so he put everything
on one קלף klaf or he's put the things in the wrong
order in the של ראש shel rosh or maybe in the של
יד shel yad he didn't make the break between the פרשיות parshiyos
correctly. So therefore three's enough but you make gotta make sure you
at least see one of each type just to make sure. It's
interesting because if you then take that logic you should have said
you need three של יד shel yad then three של ראש, shel
rosh, but presumably in principle three is enough but just gotta check
to make sure you've also you've looked at both types. And that's
why and that's and that's what you're doing there. That's because it's
all one supplier. איני aini says the גמרא Gemara is this really
true? והתני v'hasani רבה בר שמואל, Rabbah bar Shmuel, רבה בר שמואל
Rabbah bar Shmuel taught: בתפילין בודק שלש של יד ושל ראש. bitfillin
bodek shalosh shel yad v'shel rosh.
So you have to check both three של יד shel yad and
three של ראש, shel rosh, which is a reasonable position if you're
concerned that של יד shel yad does not imply של ראש shel
rosh you need three of each. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
לאו או שלש של יד או שלש של ראש? mai lav o
shalosh shel yad o shalosh shel rosh? Doesn't that mean even, now
that's an interesting read, the גמרא's Gemara going to say even I
could read that maybe sympathetically according to you to say it means
not you know any three, but at least it means, you know,
you know it doesn't mean you have to check both the של
יד shel yad and the של ראש shel rosh with three, but
that even if you're doing just three they could all be of
one type and then you could infer the other type, right? So
one way or the other it contradicts you. Either it means you
need both, which means if you're gonna if you're gonna say של
יד shel yad and של ראש shel rosh are different, I'm sorry
I don't know what that was, if you're going to say של
יד shel yad and של ראש shel rosh are different then you
would need three of each. And if you're going to say essentially
they're the same then you could satisfy with then three of one
or the other should be sufficient. So but either way it contradicts
you. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, לא, lo, no, that's
not what it means, it means שלש, shalosh, it means check a
total of three, מהן של יד ומהן של ראש, mehen shel yad
u'mehen shel rosh, some have to be from the יד yad some
from the ראש. rosh. Of course it doesn't sound that way at
all because it says שלש של יד ושל ראש, shalosh shel yad
v'shel rosh, it doesn't say שלש של יד ושל ראש shalosh shel
yad v'shel rosh which would have been a little bit more ambivalent
you know or ambiguous in terms of what it meant. Okay but
anyway it's an interesting idea that you need three and you need
to check both types but you can do a sampling of each
type. Yes, what's that? It says
בודק שלש. bodek shalosh. Oh it does. Okay thank you. So there
you go, that's why you could read it that way.
Maybe I was jumping ahead to the next point. Okay, so yeah,
it does work. It says שלש של יד ושל ראש, shalosh shel
yad v'shel rosh, so three of the של יד shel yad and
של ראש shel rosh you know a total of three from the
של יד shel yad and של ראש. shel rosh. Actually it is
a reasonable read. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
והתני רב כהנא v'hasani Rav Kahana בתפילין בודק שתים של יד ושתים
של ראש. bitfillin bodek shtayim shel yad u'shtayim shel rosh. But he
says by תפילין tfillin check two of the של יד shel yad
and two of the של ראש. shel rosh. So one way or
the other if it either means and or or but it doesn't
fit into your idea of a total of three with a sampling
of each. So the גמרא Gemara says הא מני רבי היא, ha
mani Rebbi hi, that's רבי, Rebbi, דאמר בתרי זימני הוי חזקה. d'amar
bitrei zimnei hvei chazakah. You might remember we came up to this
before in our learning that there's a debate of רבי Rebbi and
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, no who is it?
רבה בר שמואל? Rabbah bar Shmuel? רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, whether a
חזקה chazakah is two times or three times. So normally that means
whether something proves like it's habitual after two times or three times.
Here it's a question about whether you can sort of this idea
of sampling if you've seen two sort of you know two sort
of data points is that enough to extrapolate to the rest. So
this is רבי Rebbi that says two is really sufficient and maybe
and maybe you read it two of the של יד shel yad
or of the של ראש shel rosh or maybe he means he
thinks that you need separate checks for the של יד shel yad
and של ראש shel rosh two of both but whatever it is
it's not the position we're talking about. We're talking about the position
of three and three of a mix of של יד shel yad
and של ראש. shel rosh. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
אי רבי ee Rebbi if it's רבי Rebbi אימא סיפא eima seifa
look at the end of that ברייתא: braisa: וכן בצבת השני v'chein
batzeves hashaini and the same by the second pair or the second
sort of you know sort of group, וכן בצבת השלישי v'chein batzeves
hashlishi or the third group. Now what we assume that means is
that you have a couple of bags of תפילין tfillin maybe from
different suppliers and or I don't know what we'll see actually maybe
same supplier and you check two from the one bag and then
the two you know two of the של יד shel yad and
two of the של ראש shel rosh from bag one, two of
one של יד shel yad and של ראש shel rosh from bag
two and and of three and then if bags one, two and
three are all good you can extrapolate to all the bags. So
that's what how we're reading it. So why do you need three
bags to be good? After you've checked two bags you should be
able to extrapolate. Okay now I should say this is a little
funny because again the question the גמרא Gemara said before if it's
multiple suppliers you should never be able to extrapolate. If it's all
one supplier why does one bag as opposed to another bag matter?
Well like the the group that he made in you know in
January is different than the group that he made in February? So
it's not exactly clear why we think that those need to be
proven separately.
But if you assume they're online separately של ראש shel rosh and
של יד... shel yad...
Right, so the but the question of the גמרא Gemara is why
do you have to check three separate bags? Okay? So he says
like this, אי רבי שלישי מי אית ליה? ee Rebbi shlishi mi
is lei? Since when does he say that you have
to check a third bag? If you can check two pairs of
תפילין tfillin for one bag you should be able to check two
bags to extrapolate to the rest. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מודה רבי בצבתים דמיתרי תלתא גברי זבין modeh Rebbi bitzvatim d'mitrei tlasa
gavrei zavin which is the only reasonable point anyway which is no,
no, the reason you have to check bags separately is each bag
comes from a different person. Okay, but if that's true, why is
three enough? Then each bag would require separate checking. So the גמרא
Gemara says that actually, so אי הכי אפילו רביעי נמי ואפילו חמישי
נמי, ee hachi afilu reviei nami va'afilu chamishi nami, you'd have to
check bags four and five. אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, you
do. And when it says you check one, two, and you have
to check one, two, and three, it means etc. etc. You have
to check every single bag. והא דקתני שלישי, Ve'ha dekatanu shlishi, why
it says you have to check the third bag, not to tell
you after the third you're done, but to say לאפוקי מחזקי, lafukei
michizkei, to to say that it's not the normal rule of חזקה,
chazaka, meaning רבי Rebbi is saying look, here's what I say. You
got to check two from each bag, because I say two establishes
a חזקה. chazaka. And you have to check it from bag one,
and you have to check it from bag two, and you have
to check it from bag three, etc. So the way
so meaning saying every bag, but why did he say bag three?
To tell you don't think bag one and two is enough and
you can extrapolate from the two bags. You can't extrapolate from two
bags, because each bag is a different supplier. So you can extrapolate
from two תפילין tefillin for a whole bag, but not from two
bags for all the bags. So he said three to tell you,
when it comes to the bags, two won't be enough, you need
three.
Why not just say every bag?
ודאי Uvdai well okay I understand, sometimes they talk that way, לעולם
אפילו רביעי וחמישי נמי le'olam afilu reviee vechamishi nami and therefore even
four and five. Okay, so that was an interesting little digression of
doing spot checks, you know, comes up in a very serious of
הלכה halacha when you have a whole huge amount of things, comes
up like in restaurants, they get a big box crate of lettuce.
You know, can they check two or three heads or do they
have to check every single head, you know, and so on. So
this is also applying here and the person two times three times
and an interesting idea of you need של יד ושל ראש, shel
yad ve'shel rosh, both have to be checked, but maybe some type
of a mix suffices.
Okay so now it would be different because he just says שתים
של יד...
shtayim shel yad... Right. Now the גמרא Gemara says מצא צבתים או
כריכות. matza tzfashim o krichot.
Now finally back to the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says if
you found the תפילין tefillin in bundles or bags, so then you
know the משנה Mishnah basically said then you wait until it gets
dark, don't take them home. So the גמרא Gemara says first it
wants to understand the difference, מאי צבתים ומאי כריכות? mai tzfashim mai
krichot? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הן הן צבתים הן הן כריכות,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav hen hen tzfashim hen hen krichot, they're
basically the same. צבתים זוזי זוזי, Tzfashim zuzei zuzei, צבתים tzfashim is
basically a collection of תפילין tefillin that are pairs, you know, it's
like multiple, like you have של יד ושל ראש shel yad ve'shel
rosh wrapped together and a של יד ושל ראש shel yad ve'shel
rosh wrapped together and they're pairs all
in the same bag. כריכות, Krichot, bundles, is דכריכו טובא, de'krichu tuvah,
they're all wrapped together, you don't have them separated off into pairs.
But it's not really a functional difference, they're just different scenarios. Now
what happens if you find this huge bag of תפילין, tefillin, the
משנה Mishnah says don't wear it, מחשיך עליהם ומביאן. machshich aleihem u'mivian.
Then you wait, you stand there and wait until it gets dark
and you bring them home. So the גמרא Gemara wants to know
why don't you, who cares it's a bag, still wear them home.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי, ve'amai, why do you have to
do that? ליעיילינהו זוג זוג, Le'alinu zug zug, take them home pair
by pair. So אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה לדידי מפרשא לי
מיניה דאבא, Amar Rav Yitzchak berei de'Rav Yehuda l'didi mefarshe lei minei
d'abba, it was explained to me in the name of my father
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, כל שאילו מכניסן זוג זוג וכלות קודם שקיעת
החמה מכניסן זוג זוג. kol she'ilu machnisan zug zug ve'chlot kodem shkiat
hachamah machnisan zug zug. If there are the number of תפילין tefillin
is not so huge that what you can do is you can
take them in, wear them, one pair at a time and make
a dozen trips or a hundred trips and get it all done
before שבת Shabbat is over, then fine, make all of those trips.
Hopefully along the way you can get some people to help you
but whatever. Okay? If it's possible to get it all done then
you do it all, one at a time.
ואלו, Ve'ilo, but if there are so many that you might get
ninety percent done but you're not going to get a hundred percent
of it home inside before שבת Shabbat is over, מחשיך עליהם ומביאן,
machshich aleihem u'mivian, then don't do this at all, just wait there.
What's the logic? Why if you what...
You're leaving some anyway.
Right! Since anyway there's some that are going to be left, right,
so you might as well just wait for all of them. I
mean it's just your own sense of... no? Because we're assuming, we
haven't gotten yet to the second part of the משנה Mishnah where
you can't wait there. We're assuming it's an option to wait there.
So if you can wait there, so if you're not going to
be able to protect all of them anyway, what's the point of
doing this trick, because in the end it is a bit of
a trick, in order to get ninety percent and you're not going
to be able to save the last ten percent. Okay, so that's
the end of the משנה Mishnah that we're about to turn to
that, but this assumes that it is possible to stay there. So
if you're not going to do all and it's possible to stay
there, don't do any and just stay there. Okay, now we go
to the question about the next part, which is ובסכנה מכסן והולך.
u'v'sakana michasan ve'holech. If it's a סכנה, sakana, now you could say
if it's raining or whatever, but if it's a סכנה sakana you
can't wait till night, you're afraid you're going to be attacked or
whatever, it's a dangerous neighborhood or just anyway somebody's going to want
to take these תפילין, tefillin, they're expensive. So in that type of
a case where you can't stay there, then you cover them and
you go home. Presumably if a middle position were possible to take
a few pairs and then cover the rest, you would do that
as well. Yes.
It raises a question of what happens to the תפילין tefillin left
unguarded while you're carrying...
I was wondering about that too! As you're making the trip. I
guess you mean and why do we ever say do multiple trips?
Why don't we ever say if there's more than one then you're
going to be leaving some unguarded for a period of time and
you always have to be there? It's a very good question, you
know, maybe חז"ל Chazal had a little רחמנות rachmanus on you, you
know, you're not, and you know also sometimes, although as we know
this isn't really true in quite crowded places like airports or whatnot,
but you know if you're in the process of going back and
forth, people are a little bit more, you know, stay back a
little bit more, they see your, they see you're dealing with it.
But I was wondering about that, yes, that's a good question.
Were you dealing with תפילין tefillin as קודש kodesh or just as
a monetary thing?
No. It's קודש.
kodesh. Yes, so you get, you save as much as you can.
Right, you don't. You can't save five out of ten?
Yes, correct, correct.
But if it's a monetary...
No, it's because of כיסי קודש, kissei kodesh, that's clear. Okay. And
that's why the משנה Mishnah only allows תפילין tefillin and then it
adds the case of a child, which we'll talk about in a
minute, but it's clear that it's כיסי קודש. kissei kodesh. But yes,
the point is is that you is that if you can...
there's a fire in a שול. shul. Yes, yes, and you can't...
Yes, of course, you save as much as you can.
As much as you can.
Exactly.
So there's actually another option here, just to stay there.
Right, רב פפא, Rav Papa, if there's an option to save some
and not all, right, here the גמרא Gemara assumes in the first
scenario you could save all, just wait there. So if you could
save all and wait there, then you have to wait there. In
a scenario where you can't save any, there's a סכנה, sakanah, so
you wear let's say one pair and go home. In a possible
scenario where you could save twenty and not the rest, so you
would save the twenty and then you'd cover the rest, absolutely. All
right, you're right, it didn't spell out that middle case, as it
assumes one extreme or the other, but that is clearly the case.
So let's take a look at the case where you can't wait
around at all. Maybe you wear one pair home but the rest
you have to leave. ובסכנה מכסה והולך, Uvesakanah mechaseh veholech, you cover
them and you leave. So now the גמרא Gemara says, והתניא בסכנה
מוליכן פחות פחות מארבע אמות. Vehatanya besakanah molichan pachos pachos me'arba amot.
One minute, I've got another solution. Take all of the תפילין tefillin
and make multiple little little trips of four אמות amot at a
less than four אמות amot at a time, right? If you remember
the משנה Mishnah had רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon's solution. רבי שמעון's Rebbi
Shimon's solution was the daisy chain, you know, the Chinese fire drill.
You get a hundred people all in a line. But he says,
you know, actually even if you don't like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
or you don't have a hundred people, you can do it all
by yourself. You walk three אמות amot and you stop. You walk
three אמות amot and you stop, and that way you can bring
them all home. So why don't we tell you to do that
if it's a סכנה sakanah rather than just cover them and leave
it? Okay, that at least will save them. Why not do that?
And even though that's a somewhat of a rabbinic violation, I mean,
we let you do it when you're stuck outside the city with
your wallet, so we should let you do, right, if you remember
that was the end of מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, so we should
let you do it here as well. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב לא קשיא, Amar
Rav lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא בסכנת נכרי הא בסכנת ליסטין.
Ha besakanas nochri ha besakanas listin. Difference whether it's a non-Jew or
it's robbers. Now, what's the difference?
So רש"י Rashi first has a very interest... so the first way
רש"י Rashi understands is the following, is that if it's a concern
of non-Jews, then you can't cover it and leave, because if the
non-Jew finds it, he will, you know, he'll mistreat it. So you're
exposing the קדושה kedushah for being mistreated, the תפילין tefillin for being
mistreated. However, if you're just afraid of robbers, but they're good פרום
frum Jewish robbers, then you don't want to go take the whole
bundle because the robbers will find you and maybe kill you to
take the תפילין, tefillin, which are very expensive, okay? So you have
to cover, but you don't have to worry about covering it and
leaving it because once they find the תפילין, tefillin, they'll be careful
about the קדושה kedushah of the תפילין. tefillin. Okay?
I kid you not, this is what רש"י Rashi says. בסכנת ליסטין.
Besakanas listin. I could not say this better than רש"י. Rashi. He
says ישראל, Yisrael, so a Jewish robber, דקטלי ליה משום ממונא, dekatlei
lei mishum mamona, they would kill you for the money, so you
can't carry them home less and less than four אמות amot because
you'll be attacked, but you can cover them, ותפילין לא מבזו להו,
vetephillin lo mevazu lehu, but they're going to take the תפילין tefillin
very in a very appropriate way. So the problems we had about
פרומקייט frumkeit expressing itself only in the בין אדם למקום bein adam
lemakom were issues that have been with us for a while. But
I know, but before we go on, I do want to say
that רש"י Rashi ultimately rejects that פשט pshat in this גמרא Gemara
because of the continuation of the discussion. And the continuation of this
discussion רש"י Rashi says is what the גמרא Gemara means is the
following. סכנת נכרי Sakanas nochri means you can't... you're afraid to carry
them or wear them because there's a שעת השמד sha'as hashmad and
Jews caught wearing תפילין tefillin are in trouble, you know, with the
non-Jews. So if that's true, you can't wear them or carry them,
the only thing you can do is cover them and go home.
That's the משנה. Mishnah. However, when it says you do this less
less four אמות, amot, that's you're only concerned about people robbing you.
You're not... so therefore if you're not concerned about them being found
on you, it's not that the non-Jews are going to get you
in trouble if they're found on you, then you do this trick
of less than four אמות. amot. Okay? So that's a very easy
distinction, what type of a danger. If it's a danger that you
can carry it in little trips, you do the little trips. If
it's a danger that they can't be found on your person at
all, then you cover it and you leave it. So now the
גמרא Gemara says top of צ"ז
עמוד ב'. tzaddi zayin amud bet. אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye.
במאי אוקימתא למתניתין? Bemai okimta lamatnitin? What did you say our משנה
Mishnah was talking about? בסכנת עובדי גלולים. Besakanat ovdei gilulim. by a
סכנה sakana of robbers. So אימא סיפא aima seifa let’s look at
the end. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, I mean not robbers, I misread
that, by סכנה sakana of non-Jews that you’re afraid to have תפילין
tefillin found on you or on your person and you have to
walk away from them. So then אימא סיפא aima seifa but how
do you then explain the suggestion of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or
the position of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? What does רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon say? רבי שמעון אומר נותן לחבירו וחבירו לחבירו. Rabbi Shimon omer
nosein l’chaveiro v’chaveiro l’chaveiro. So he says you do this whole daisy
chain. So how can you do a daisy chain
if the non-Jews are going to get you know or going to
attack you if you’re wearing תפילין tefillin if you’re dealing with תפילין?
tefillin? So כל שכן דאוושא מילתא. kol shekein d’avsha milsa. That certainly
should be problematic. It makes a big public event out of it.
So how can you say the משנה mishna is a case where
there’s an edict of not to wear תפילין tefillin or not to
be dealing with תפילין tefillin then what’s רבי שמעון’s Rabbi Shimon suggestion?
The גמרא gemara says no, חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasuri mechasra v’hachi
kasani. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon isn’t going on that case. He’s going
on an earlier case. Here’s how you should understand it. במה דברים
אמורים בסכנת עובדי כוכבים? Bamei devarim amurim bisakanas ovdei kochavim? When did
we say, meaning it’s reading this into the משנה, mishna, cover it
and leave when you’re afraid about a non-Jew they have an edict
out and you can’t be seen with תפילין tefillin then cover it
and leave.
אבל בסכנת ליסטים Aval bisakanas listim but if it’s just a concern
about the תפילין tefillin being robbed then מוליכן פחות פחות מארבע אמות
molichan pachos pachos m’arba amos you take little trips and on that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I don’t like the little trip idea
I want to do the daisy chain instead. Okay so now so
now we have the following: if you can’t have תפילין tefillin found
on you you just cover it. If you can’t save them all
and it’s possible to wait you wait. If it’s not possible to
wait and you’re not afraid of them being found on you what
do you do? Then there’s a debate of the תנא קמא tanna
kamma and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. תנא קמא Tanna kamma says little
trips less than ארבע אמות arba amos and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says this daisy chain. So now the גמרא gemara wants to understand
what is that debate about? So let’s take a look. רבי שמעון
אומר נותן לחבירו Rabbi Shimon omer nosein l’chaveiro you give it to
the friend and you do this this Chinese fire drill. במאי קמיפלגי?
Bimai kamiflagi? What’s the debate? מר סבר פחות מארבע אמות עדיף. Mar
savar pachos m’arba amos adif. So the תנא קמא tanna kamma holds
it’s better for you to do it yourself and make little trips
less than ארבע אמות. arba amos. Why? דאי אמרת נותן לחבירו וחבירו
לחבירו D’ei amart nosein l’chaveiro v’chaveiro l’chaveiro עדיף adif if
I’m sorry וחבירו לחבירו אוושא מילתא דשבת. v’chaveiro l’chaveiro avsha milsa d’shabbos.
It would make it very public and forget the non-Jews it’s not
as respectful of שבת. shabbos. Right? You’re making a whole big commotion
on שבת shabbos and the commotion is about doing this trick way
of carrying. So I’d rather keep it all very quiet. So that’s
why I want you to do it yourself. I don’t want you
to do this whole thing which involves a lot of people. So
what’s רבי שמעון’s Rabbi Shimon position? ומר סבר Umar savar on the
other hand holds נותן לחבירו עדיף. nosein l’chaveiro adif. No it’s better
to do this thing of giving it to your friend and so
on. דאי אמרת מוליכן פחות פחות מארבע אמות D’ei amart molichan pachos
pachos m’arba amos if you say you should take it less than
ארבע אמות arba amos in multiple trips זימנין דלאו אדעתיה. zimnin d’lav
adateih. There are times you’re not thinking you know you’re not paying
close attention you forget for a moment and you take a few
extra steps ואתי לאתויי ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים v’asi l’asu-ei arba amos
birshus harabbim and you’ll come to carry. Okay so this actually is
quite a lovely conceptual debate right? It’s almost a type of a
tradeoff between sort of concern about the public experience of שבת shabbat
or the personal violation. What’s going to motivate us more? Are we
going to try to more protect the you know the the the
texture of שבת shabbat and even if it raises a risk that
you personally might violate you’re not going to violate במזיד b’meizid anyway
the most will be בשוגג bishogeg or are we going to focus
on you the individual and your possible violation and do everything to
protect you from that even if it somewhat you know makes שבת
shabbat a little bit less you know the right you know the
right quality for everybody else and somewhat violates somewhat of the spirit
of שבת? shabbat? And you know this is much
of what you’re doing though.
What you’re doing well yeah well it’s only מותר muttar in a
special circumstance you know. But it’s but whatever first of all just
makes a lot of commotion on שבת shabbat which is itself not
ideal. And number two it’s what do you call it? It’s you
know it might mislead people to think you can always do something
like this. So it’s an interesting question of which side do we
weigh on. You know there’s an interesting debate of the ראשונים rishonim
both רמב״ם Rambam and the רמב״ן Ramban say that there is a
biblical מצוה mitzvah of although רמב״ם’s Rambam a little vaguer but anyway
it sounds like he’s saying that there’s a biblical מצוה mitzvah of
like you know תשבות. tishbos. You should rest on שבת shabbat that
goes beyond the ל״ט מלאכות. lamed tet melachos. So what does it
mean there beyond the ל״ט מלאכות? lamed tet melachos? So the רמב״ן
Ramban says it means that you should make sure that it’s a
restful day not a day of exertion and you should you know
do the things that are the quality of the nature of שבת
shabbat and preserving the nature of the day even if it’s completely
unrelated to the מלאכות. melachos. The רמב״ם Rambam says no תשבות tishbos
is telling you don’t do activities that might lead you to transgress
the מלאכות. melachos. So it’s very interesting you know about whether your
emphasis is completely about the technical הלכה halacha and the possibility of
transgressing that and even if there’s a quality of שבת shabbat it’s
protecting the מלאכות melachos or is there a or are you you
know weighing seriously this quality of שבת shabbat outside of the specific
issue of transgressing this or that הלכה. halacha. So to some degree,
Take little steps, maybe you would violate, but it preserves the quality
of שבת, Shabbat, or make a big deal out of it, which
challenges the quality of שבת, Shabbat, but protects people from possible inadvertent
violation.
And you practically understand how taking little steps is not a violation,
but if you're really concerned about highwaymen, and you have to take
little steps and you have to rest,
you're
only concerned about it being stolen if it's unguarded. Okay, presumably it's
a scenario where you're not concerned about being mugged, you're concerned about
just somebody taking it if it's being unguarded. Just highwaymen? Yeah, that's
the scenario in the גמרא. Gemara. That you have to assume. If
you're afraid that even taking it, somebody will find out about it
and attack you, whatever, then of course, then you're making the situation
worse by taking it home. Both the תפילין tefillin are being exposed
to danger and you. Okay, so now the משנה Mishna goes on,
that's the תפילין tefillin case. Then it says, oh, the same would
happen about your child, you would pass it from hand to hand
to bring him back home, so him or her. So the גמרא
Gemara says בנו מאי בעי התם? Bno mai ba'ei hasam? What what
what's your kid doing there? What, you were walking the field and
you found your kid? So the גמרא Gemara says דבי מנשיה תנא,
de-bei Menashya tana, so דבי מנשיה de-bei Menashya teaches a ברייתא braita
that clarifies this: בשילדתו אמו בשדה. be-she-yeldato imo ba-sadeh. So that's what
רש"י Rashi said when we did the משנה. Mishna.
Yeah, he was given birth out in the field, and before שבת
Shabbat and you didn't have a chance to bring, you know, to
bring him home on שבת. Shabbat. Now, of course, I
understood everybody said סכנת נפשות, sakanat nefashot, and, you know, what can
I say? If there's a סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot issue, and doing
this type of a thing would in any way,
you know,
be risky, then of course you don't do it. The גמרא Gemara
is assuming, although I realize it's a bizarre sort of scenario it's
assuming, that there's no סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot issue. Okay, but you
still—or if you want to say it, even if there is a
סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot issue, you try, if there's a way to
do it without violating שבת, Shabbat, you do it, and doing this
will not actually—the kid is not in a state where there's any
where it would expose him to any danger.
Of course he is. A newborn baby needs to nurse.
I know, but it doesn't mean that has to be there. Right,
but does it mean that? You have to get him home? Does
it mean that one person has to put him under his arm
and run home with him, or does it mean you can take
twenty minutes to do this little process? You know, so that's the
point. The point is, is that it's assuming a scenario where doing
this does not increase any risk. So, of course, you're getting him
home, but if you can do it in a כשר kosher way,
in a more כשר kosher way, better to do it that way.
But they're comparing the baby to the תפילין. tefillin.
They're comparing it to special cases which we would obviously—baby is more
important—but they're talking about special cases which we would, you have to
protect something or someone and do it in the way that, you
know, that doesn't violate שבת. Shabbat. If, again, doing it this way
increases any risk, obviously you would not. You have to assume that.
The גמרא Gemara goes on to say: Wait a minute, ומאי אפילו
הן מאה? u-mai afilu hen me'ah? What does it mean, even if
there's a hundred people that are part of this chain? דאף על
גב דקשיא ליה ידא? de-af al gav de-kashya lei yada? Now this,
of course, challenges what I just told you. Even though it's hard
for him the hand—meaning it's so much handling, being handed off from
one person to the next, not necessarily the best thing, you know,
to do for an infant—אפילו הכי הדי, afilu hachi hadi, for that's
better. So that actually does challenge what I'm saying, right, which is
it's surprising because, as we know, you know, the גמרא Gemara is
very extreme in the principle of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. So somehow
you have to assume that the גמרא Gemara means that this is
unpleasant but not risky,
for
the baby, but not risky.
Because they did not really consider newborns till they reached a month,
I think.
That is not true by issues of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. By
פיקוח נפש—I pikuach nefesh know, but I'm saying the גמרא Gemara does
not spell out what the status is, and you have to assume
that the גמרא Gemara is working with the assumption.
But they're saying even if it's difficult, but
they're not saying
פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. I don't know what to say. The גמרא
Gemara is clear that you're מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbat for the sake
of a newborn.
Okay. Yeah, or even—even a fetus, you would be מחלל שבת. mechalel
Shabbat.
אם מוליכו פחות פחות מארבע אמות. im molicho pachos pachos me-arba amot.
So this is just רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon position. The חכמים Chachamim
would say פחות פחות. pachos pachos. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, let's move on from the infant. רבי יהודה אומר נותן אדם
חבית. Rabbi Yehuda omer nosein adam chavit. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you can do the same daisy chain thing with a barrel.
And the חכמים Chachamim said back to him: No, no, no, you
can't do that, because you're taking it outside of the תחום. techum.
Because, you know, he said even if the barrel is outside of
the תחום, techum, they said, how can you take something outside of
the תחום? techum? Now the question, before you get to the תחום
techum issue, is, until now we've been talking about ספרי תורה sifrei
Torah or babies. Since when can you do it for simply money
purposes? A barrel, right? Presumably, barrels often contain wine or oil, so
presumably, you're just doing it to protect—From the highwaymen? No, no, you
know, so since when is that allowed? Now, it could be, you
know, again, remember the משנה Mishna at the end of שבת Shabbat
said if you're stuck outside the city with your wallet, the משנה
Mishna actually didn't say, the משנה Mishna said there's a secret, you
know, there's some other thing to do, or the גמרא Gemara said,
we're not going to tell you, you know, but we didn't initially
say it out loud, and that was this פחות פחות. pachos pachos.
So sometimes that's allowed for money, but that's when you're very anxious
or concerned you're going to
lose— So the question, there’s two questions here. Number one, what happened
to תחום? Tchum? Why, how come he doesn’t pay attention to that?
But number two, why is the barrel a special case of allowing
something like this? So let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. ולית
ליה לרבי יהודה הא דתנן, V’leis lei l’Rabbi Yehuda ha ditnan, first
of all how does Rabbi Yehuda ignore the תחום Tchum issue? Does
he not hold that which we taught in the
משנה Mishna הבהמה והכלים כרגלי הבעלים, Ha’behema v’hakeilim k’raglei ha’bealim, that animals
you own and vessels you own are like your legs, are limited
by as far as you can go? So they’re defined by your
תחום. Tchum. So if this barrel to bring it to a safe
place would leave your תחום, Tchum, you’re not allowed to do it.
אמר ריש לקיש משום לוי סבא, Amar Reish Lakish mishum Levi Saba,
Reish Lakish said in the name of Levi the elder, interesting. הכא
במאי עסקינן, Hacha b’mai askinan, what are we talking about? דמערה מחבית
לחבית, D’meara m’chavis l’chavis, that you don’t actually take the barrel, you
make a, even talk about a real Chinese fire drill, everybody’s got
their own barrel. Now how did everybody get a barrel out there
to do this? I have no idea, but okay, everybody had a
barrel and you poured it from one barrel to the next and
I poured from one barrel to the next and I poured from
one barrel to the next. Okay, I don’t know how we got
all those barrels out there. Now the question is why does that
better? You’re still moving the water or the wine or whatever, that’s
still a תחום Tchum issue even if the barrel isn’t.
פחות פחות מד' אמות
Pachos pachos
mi’daled amos maybe? Maybe.
Anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this. So, but now how come
the liquid isn’t a problem? Because
רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאמר מים אין בהן ממש. Rabbi Yehuda l’taameih d’amar
mayim ein bahen mamash. So the barrel you’re not moving חוץ לתחום
Chutz l’tchum and the liquid that you are moving, and we’re assuming
here it’s water, which by the way helps explain why we’re allowing
you to do it because it might be that you need drinking
water. Okay, and
if it’s only water, water’s not significant and water isn’t limited by
תחום Tchum issues. How do you know that?
העברת עציץ Haavaras atzitz right?
Right. So the גמרא's Gemara's not going to stick with this. Okay
so let’s take a look. Good memory. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, דתנן Ditnan רבי יהודה פוטר במים מפני שאין בהן ממש.
Rabbi Yehuda poter b’mayim mipnei she’ein bahen mamash. Rabbi Yehuda exempts the
water, it’s not significant. Now what’s the scenario? The scenario is that
I’m kneading dough, as I do every ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, and
I go to Michael and I get some water from Michael to
make my חלה. Challah. What is the תחום Tchum of that חלה?
Challah? So the חכמים Chachamim say it’s limited by the overlap of
Michael’s תחום Tchum and my תחום Tchum because it has in it
ingredients from both of us. So you understand right? So if Michael’s
תחום Tchum goes that way and mine goes that way and there’s
a limited overlap it’s limited. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no,
it’s not limited by Michael’s תחום, Tchum, the water wasn’t significant. So
the גמרא Gemara assumes if the water wasn’t significant in that case,
water for him never has תחום Tchum issues. Of course there’s a
huge difference right? Which the גמרא Gemara is about to say. It’s
one thing when the water becomes an invisible ingredient, it’s another thing
when you’re dealing with the water in its actual state. So the
גמרא Gemara says
ומאי לא תהלך זו? U’mai lo teilech zu? And what does it
mean when the חכמים Chachamim say no you can’t take it out
of the תחום? Tchum? לא תהלך מה שבזו, Lo teilech mah she’b’zu,
they don’t mean it, the barrel, they mean you can’t take the
thing in it out of the תחום, Tchum, יותר מרגלי הבעלים. Yoser
mei’raglei ha’bealim. So fine, so that’s the issue, the issue is can
you move the, does water have the תחום Tchum issue? The גמרא
Gemara says no, that cannot be the case. אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי
יהודה היכא דבליען בעיסה. Eima d’shamas lei l’Rabbi Yehuda heicha d’belian b’isa.
When did Rabbi Yehuda say water’s insignificant? If it’s absorbed in the
dough, it’s basically completely invisible. אבל היכא דאיתנהו בעינייהו, Aval heicha d’isneihu
b’einihu, when they’re in their own, you know, in their original state,
when they’re by themselves, מי שמעת ליה? Mi shamas lei? Since when
did he say there’s no תחום Tchum issue? השתא בקדירה אמר רבי
יהודה לא בטילי. Hashta b’kdeira amar Rabbi Yehuda lo betili. Rabbi Yehuda
even says that if water in a pot, if you’re making stew,
the water of that stew has the הלכות Halachos of עירוב. Eiruv.
So if that’s true, בעינייהו בטלי? B’einihu batli? Then by themselves they
would be significant? Now how do you know he says the water
of a stew? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Braita, רבי
יהודה אומר מים ומלח בטילים בעיסה. Rabbi Yehuda omer mayim u’melach betilim
b’isa. The water and the salt are nullified in the dough and
don’t have the laws of תחומין. Tchumin. ואין בטילים בקדירה, V’ein betilim
b’kdeira, but not in a stew, in a pot, מפני רוטבא Mipnei
rotva because of the sauce. The sauce is independent and therefore it
has תחום Tchum issues. So by saying that what’s in the barrel
is water and it’s רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not help. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has תחום Tchum for water. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so back to the question, what about the תחום Tchum issue?
אלא אמר רבא הכא בחבית שקנתה שביתה ומים שלא קנו שביתה עסקינן.
Ela amar Rava hacha b’chavis she’kansah shevisa u’mayim she’lo kanu shevisa askinan.
The barrel was קונה שביתה, Koneh shevisa, did establish its place when
שבת Shabbat began, the water did not.
Now how did the water not establish its place? רש"י Rashi says,
rainwater or you drew it from a river. So you drew the
water on שבת, Shabbat, and if you draw the water from a
river where it’s flowing water, the water never had, was in a
תחום, Tchum, it is not defined by a תחום. Tchum. Okay so
that solves the water problem. But again back to the question, other
than assuming there were a hundred empty barrels lined up, you took
the water with the barrel. So what about the problem of the
barrel? The גמרא Gemara says ah, once there’s no problem with the
water, there’s no problem with the barrel because the thing that matters
here was the water, the barrel is just the container. So the
תחום Tchum is defined by the תחום Tchum of the water, not
the תחום Tchum of the barrel. And that’s the next point. So
once the water doesn’t have a תחום, Tchum, the barrel also not.
דבטיל חבית לגבי מים, d'vateil hachavis l'gabei mayim, and then the barrel
is negated, is secondary to the water.
So you don't need the hundred barrels?
You don't need the hundred barrels, we're back to a simple פשט
pshat of the משנה, mishna, כדתנן, k'ditnan, like we talk about this
in other scenarios, not just תחום techum issues but even carrying issues.
המוציא חי במטה פטור אף על המטה. hamotzi chai b'mita patur af
al hamita. If somebody takes a live person out in a bed,
like on a stretcher, you're exempt even for the bed. The live
person you're exempt because חי נושא את עצמו, chai nosei es atzmo,
he's considered to be lifting himself, supporting his own weight. But you're
also exempt on the bed. Why am I exempt for taking the
bed out?
מפני שהמטה טפילה לו, mipnei shehamita tfeila lo, because the bed is
not seen as—I didn't take the bed out, I really took the
person out. He's the only thing that's important. The bed is secondary.
So if I'm exempt on the person, I'm also exempt on the
bed. You don't treat the bed separate from the person.
Similarly, המוציא אוכלין פחות מכשיעור בכלי. hamotzi ochlin pachas mikishiur b'kli. If
I take out—remember there's a minimum size of taking things out,
כגרוגרת—and k'gogeres if I take out less than the minimum amount, I
take out a tiny bit of an apple in a vessel, so
I'm not חייב chayav on the food, but let me be חייב
chayav on the vessel, on the bowl. No, פטור אף על הכלי,
patur af al hakli, you're exempt even on the bowl, מפני שהכלי
טפל לו, mipnei shehakli tafel lo, because the—it's secondary. So it's basically
seen like an apple with its container, and it's defined by the
apple. And if you're exempt on the apple, you're exempt on the
bowl. So same here, it's water in its container. And if water
doesn't have a תחום, techum, then the container doesn't have a תחום.
techum. And that's the solution. Okay, so מתיב רב יוסף, masiv Rav
Yosef, so Rav Yosef asked on this:
we have a ברייתא. braisa. Here's what the ברייתא braisa says. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, בשיירא, b'shayara, if you're in a caravan,
so you really have no access to water, it's a special case,
נותן מים וחבית לחברו וחברו לחברו. nosein mayim v'chavis l'chaveiro v'chaveiro l'chaveiro.
So then you do this whole daisy chain. בשיירא אין שלא בשיירא
לא. b'shayara in shelo b'shayara lo. It sounds like you're only allowed
this in a caravan. So it's just a סתם stam question, in
the ברייתא braisa he says a caravan and in the משנה mishna
he doesn't. What's the case? So הגמרא hagemara says, אלא אמר רב
יוסף, ela amar Rav Yosef, כי תנן נמי במתניתין בשיירא תנן. ki
tnan nami b'misnisin b'shayara tnan. But this is how it helps him.
Ah, since in the ברייתא braisa he says a caravan, I'll say
the משנה mishna is a caravan, and therefore what? Now I've solved
the תחום techum problem. How do you solve the תחום techum problem?
Because if you're talking about a caravan, this gets to you—פיקוח נפש,
pikuach nefesh, סכנת נפשות. sakanas nefashos. You're talking about water as not
just a luxury, you're talking about water as a real need. So
Rabbi Yehuda says I'm not going to care about תחום. techum. I'll
care about carrying, I'll do a trick, whatever I'll do, but I'm
not going to care about תחום techum if you basically have a
caravan that doesn't have water. So that's how you solve the תחום
techum problem. Not a special case of water that was drawn from
a river that doesn't have a תחום. techum. Okay, אביי אמר, Abaye
amar, now Abaye says yes, I agree that the caravan has special
allowances but not as much as you say. בשיירא אפילו חבית שקנתה
שביתה ומים שקנו שביתה. b'shayara afilu chavis shekansah shvisa u'mayim shekanu shvisa.
If you're the caravan, then even if the water is being taken
out of the תחום, techum, I'll concede that point. Okay, but I
don't want to give up the other point. שלא בשיירא, shelo b'shayara,
if it's not a caravan, you're in the city but you still
need water, maybe it's not as urgent or whatever, but you still
need the water, then חבית שקנתה שביתה ומים שלא קנו שביתה. chavis
shekansah shvisa u'mayim shelo kanu shvisa. Then it would be the scenario
that we talked about with the water did not have a תחום.
techum. So basically he says there are two cases: there's a case
of the משנה, mishna, the case of the ברייתא. braisa. They're not
all one. You are right in the case of the ברייתא, braisa,
the caravan, Rabbi Yehuda's position is I don't care about תחום. techum.
But the case of the משנה mishna is not the caravan. And
there Rabbi Yehuda—and there the scenario is why does he not care
about תחום techum in that case when it's not a caravan? That's
because it's a case where the water was drawn on שבת Shabbos
and the water did not have a שביתה. shvisa. And that's the
position. Yeah, but Abaye's just clarifying: don't say it's all a special
case of a caravan. Caravan is a special case, but it's not
the case we're talking about. Okay,
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, הכא בחבית דהפקר עסקינן ומים דהפקר
עסקינן. hacha b'chavis d'hefker askinan u'mayim d'hefker askinan. They're ownerless, it's an
ownerless barrel and water. And ownerless barrel and water don't have a
תחום techum because תחום techum is defined by their owner. ומאן אמרו
לה, u'man amru lah, and who is the one that therefore says
"What about the
תחום techum issue?" רבי יוחנן בן נורי היא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
hi, דאמר חפצי הפקר קונין שביתה, d'amar cheftzei hefker konin shvisa, because
he actually says that even ownerless objects have their own 2000 אמה,
amah, not defined by their owner, they're defined by 2000 אמה amah
from where they started. Okay, so now we understand the debate? Rabbi
Yehuda says they were ownerless so I'm not worried about תחום, techum,
and the other one says "What about תחום?" techum? because I think
even ownerless objects have a
תחום. techum. ומאי לא תהלך זו יותר מרגלי הבעלים? u'mai lo sehalech
zu yoser me'raglei habaalim? So then what does it mean to say
they can't go further than their owners? You said the case was
an owner. It means לא יהלכו אלו יותר מכלים שיש להם בעלים,
lo yehalechu elu yoser mi'keilim sheyesh lahem baalim, it means these are
no better than objects that are owned. So don't tell me you're
not concerned about תחום techum because they're ownerless, they're just the same
as objects that are owned and they have תחום. techum. Okay, so
that was a case of three things that we allowed: ספר תורה,
sefer Torah, baby (with all the acknowledgment of the problem of סכנת
נפשות), sakanas nefashos and water. And water in two scenarios: one is
for caravan that obviously there's a dire need that you go ahead
and—don't worry about תחום techum issues at all. And then water where
there's less of a dire need and there's this debate of how
do you—do you worry about תחום? techum? Is there a special case
because it's—nobody owns it, or you drew it on שבת, Shabbos, that
allows to address the תחום techum issue. Now we move on to
the next משנה mishnah which gets us to a continued theme of
special allowances for the sake of protecting כתבי קודש. kisvei kodesh. So
let's take a look.
היה קורא בספר על האיסקופא, Haya kore b’sefer al ha-iskopa, you were
reading on a book, now book doesn't necessarily have to mean a
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but let's anyway assume that it is some
type of a scroll, but it is, we're going to assume for
argument's sake that it's a scroll of some form of כתבי קודש,
kisvei kodesh, and it is a scroll, it's not a book, and
you're reading on the porch. ונתגלגל הספר מידו, V’nisgalgal ha-sefer mi-yado, and
it rolled out of your hand, it dropped out of your hand
and it rolled down, and now you have half of the scroll
like hanging over the balcony, right, you know, you're on a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, this is a שבת Shabbos case, you're here in
your balcony on the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, you're reading, you know,
and now it's hanging down and down there's the רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. Can you roll it back up to you? What do you
do? So,
וגוללו אצלו, v’gololo etzlo, so you're still holding on to one end,
you can roll it back up. היה קורא בראש הגג ונתגלגל הספר
מידו, Haya kore b’rosh ha-gag v’nisgalgal ha-sefer mi-yado, seems like an almost
identical case, you're on the roof and it fell out of your
hand and it rolled and you're still holding on to one end.
עד שלא הגיע לעשרה טפחים, Ad she-lo higia l’asara tfachim, as long
as the bottom, the part that's hanging down is not within the
ten טפחים tfachim of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, because you'll remember, higher
than ten טפחים tfachim of רשות הרבים reshus harabim is not a
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it's a מקום פטור, makom p’tor, so then
you're not removing it to roll it up would not be to
remove it from a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So in that case,
גוללו אצלו, gololo etzlo, you wrap, you rolled it up. משהגיע לעשרה
טפחים, Mishe-higia l’asara tfachim, but once one end of it is hanging
in the airspace of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, we're not going to
let you roll it up. So what do you do? הופכו על
הכתב, Hofcho al ha-ksav, you turn the script part to the wall
so it's not exposed to the elements and you, that's it, you've
done what you can do. So you can't roll it up, so
what do you do? At least turn it over so the script
part is facing the wall and is more protected from the elements.
Talking where you're still holding the end.
You're still holding one end, right. That's why in theory you could
roll it up because you're holding one end, but if they're not
going to allow you to roll it up, you can turn it
over at least so that now the script faces the wall. Now
it's not clear by the way why the גג gag case is
different than the אכסדרה. achsarda. The אכסדרה achsarda says roll it up,
no limitations. The גג gag will start talking about within ten טפחים
tfachim or not within ten טפחים. tfachim. So the גמרא Gemara will
discuss that. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו אינו מסולק מן הארץ אלא כמלא
מחט, Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu eino mesulak min ha-aretz ela k’mlo machat,
even if it's only a needle's width, you know, a millimeter we
would say off the ground, as long as it's not touching the
ground you can roll it up even if it's within ten טפחים
tfachim of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. גוללו אצלו. Gololo etzlo. רבי שמעון
אומר אפילו בארץ, Rabbi Shimon omer afilu ba-aretz, even if it is
touching the ground of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, you can roll it
up because it's not fully in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, one end
of it is where you are. So he would go so far
to allow it even if it's actually has landed at one end
is resting in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. אפילו בארץ עצמו גוללו אצלו
שאין לך דבר משום שבות עומד בפני כתבי קודש, Afilu ba-aretz atzmo
גוללו אצלו she-ein l’cha davar mishum shvus omed bifnei kisvei kodesh, we're
not going to let any rabbinic prohibition get in the way of
עומד בפני כתבי קודש, omed bifnei kisvei kodesh, get in the way
of holy scriptures. So here it's very nice where the first משנה
mishnah was tricks but not actually overstepping any rabbinic prohibition although maybe
the תחום tchum chose, here we're saying that we're actually at least
according to the last position, the most lenient one of רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, we're going to let you violate rabbinic restrictions to protect
כתבי קודש. kisvei kodesh. But not the שבת. Shabbos. No, of course
for a שבת. Shabbos. Okay, and we will, so we will continue
then.